<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>quick-tips on smutek.net</title>
    <link>https://smutek.net/tags/quick-tips/</link>
    <description>Recent content in quick-tips on smutek.net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2017 17:18:36 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://smutek.net/tags/quick-tips/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Rich Semantic Titles in WordPress with ACF</title>
      <link>https://smutek.net/rich-semantic-titles-in-wordpress-with-acf/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2017 17:18:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://smutek.net/rich-semantic-titles-in-wordpress-with-acf/</guid>
      <description>Last night while browsing the Roots Discourse I came across a cool share by a user who has written a little utility to handle a request he often gets from designers and content creators.
User MWDelaney writes -
So he wrote this cool little plugin that gives end users a set of fields to construct these complex titles. The post is here, and you can check his plugin out here. I&amp;rsquo;d suggest exploring his GitHub further as it looks like he&amp;rsquo;s working on lot&amp;rsquo;s of cool ideas like this.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to restore the Bootstrap nav in Sage 8.2</title>
      <link>https://smutek.net/how-to-restore-the-bootstrap-nav-in-sage-8-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2015 17:23:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://smutek.net/how-to-restore-the-bootstrap-nav-in-sage-8-2/</guid>
      <description>As of Sage 8.2 the Bootstrap navigation has been removed. This is part of Sage&amp;rsquo;s move towards framework agnosticism. There&amp;rsquo;s good discussion here, on the GitHub pull request.
As of now, adding the navigation back is super easy, and Ben Word links to everything you&amp;rsquo;ll need to do this at the bottom of the same discussion, here.
Adding the nav back is so easy that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t really warrant a video, but I like making videos, so here&amp;rsquo;s a quick walk through.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to set up a WordPress Backup Plugin</title>
      <link>https://smutek.net/how-to-set-up-a-wordpress-backup-plugin/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Mar 2015 15:50:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://smutek.net/how-to-set-up-a-wordpress-backup-plugin/</guid>
      <description>Backups are so important Part of a series of posts from my days of self employment.
This week I&amp;rsquo;m going to cover how to set up a WordPress backup plugin. Think of this as a form of disaster insurance. Nobody knows more than you just how important your website is to the health of your business. It&amp;rsquo;s just super important to make sure that you have a proper backup of your WordPress website; not just your files, but your database as well.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Change the way WordPress inserts images</title>
      <link>https://smutek.net/change-the-way-wordpress-inserts-images/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2015 23:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://smutek.net/change-the-way-wordpress-inserts-images/</guid>
      <description>What&amp;rsquo;s the deal here? Part of a series of posts from my days of self employment.
This week I want to do a quick tip to show you how to change the way that WordPress inserts images. What I mean by this is that, by default, every time you insert an image into one of your WordPress posts, WordPress will default to linking to the image.
This is the default setting.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
