<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>smutek.net</title>
    <link>https://smutek.net/</link>
    <description>Recent content on smutek.net</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 07:25:56 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://smutek.net/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Xdebuggin at WordCamp Baltimore 2017</title>
      <link>https://smutek.net/xdebug/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 07:25:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://smutek.net/xdebug/</guid>
      <description>Thanks Today I had the honor to speak at WordCamp Baltimore on the topic of using Xdebug to write better PHP. Thanks so much to the organizers, volunteers, and attendees for having me. I hope I was able to provide some value.
My slides are here: https://slides.com/smutek/xdebug/
And notes on my presentation are below.
What is Xdebug Xdebug is a PHP extension that provides expanded profiling and tracing capabilities beyond those provided natively by PHP.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Home Office</title>
      <link>https://smutek.net/open-home-office/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jun 2017 22:49:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://smutek.net/open-home-office/</guid>
      <description>Man, it&amp;rsquo;s been many moons since my last blog post. I&amp;rsquo;m going to break that dry spell and start posting regularly again, and I thought I&amp;rsquo;d kick off with a quick one.
Here&amp;rsquo;s a link that&amp;rsquo;s just too good not to share.
Open Home Office (YC S17) Raises $7M To Bring Office Distractions To Remote Workers Nationwide
Highlights:
 Enjoy working from home, but yearn for the interminable stimulation and irritation of an open office?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Filtering the WordPress Custom Logo</title>
      <link>https://smutek.net/filtering-the-wordpress-custom-logo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2017 19:10:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://smutek.net/filtering-the-wordpress-custom-logo/</guid>
      <description>WordPress 4.5 added the custom logo feature. It&amp;rsquo;s pretty nice, and where possible I try to use native WordPress functionality, but the default markup returned by get_custom_logo() isn&amp;rsquo;t always what I&amp;rsquo;m looking for. Fortunately there&amp;rsquo;s a filter included just for this.
I build my sites with Sage, most of them using Bootstrap for the front end. Here&amp;rsquo;s a little function I wrote to leverage the native Custom Logo function, and give me back the markup I want.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shut the fuck up and go and build something</title>
      <link>https://smutek.net/shut-the-fuck-up-and-go-and-build-something/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Feb 2017 01:46:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://smutek.net/shut-the-fuck-up-and-go-and-build-something/</guid>
      <description>Check out this interview with Ghost founder John O&amp;rsquo;Nolan. It was interesting to read about the history of the project, but I thought this was a fantastic takeaway -
 What&amp;rsquo;s your advice for indie hackers who are just starting out?
Honestly my single piece of advice would probably be to stop looking for so much advice.
Shut the fuck up and go and build something.
I see so many people devouring startup books and blog posts and talking about them incessantly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Posters of your GitHub contributions</title>
      <link>https://smutek.net/posters-of-your-github-contributions/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2017 03:11:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://smutek.net/posters-of-your-github-contributions/</guid>
      <description>One would have to be a pretty major geek to want to buy a poster of their GitHub contribution heat map&amp;hellip;
Pretty cool, I think I&amp;rsquo;m going to get mine in blue! :)
CommitPrint
 via Hacker News  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rich Semantic Titles in WordPress with ACF</title>
      <link>https://smutek.net/rich-semantic-titles-in-wordpress-with-acf/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2017 17:18:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://smutek.net/rich-semantic-titles-in-wordpress-with-acf/</guid>
      <description>Last night while browsing the Roots Discourse I came across a cool share by a user who has written a little utility to handle a request he often gets from designers and content creators.
User MWDelaney writes -
So he wrote this cool little plugin that gives end users a set of fields to construct these complex titles. The post is here, and you can check his plugin out here. I&amp;rsquo;d suggest exploring his GitHub further as it looks like he&amp;rsquo;s working on lot&amp;rsquo;s of cool ideas like this.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Getting Old(er) In Tech</title>
      <link>https://smutek.net/on-getting-older-in-tech/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Dec 2016 12:58:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://smutek.net/on-getting-older-in-tech/</guid>
      <description>This was a great read, full of sage advice for kids of all ages (and professions). :)
My main takeaways - Keep learning, keep growing, stay healthy, be yourself.
On Getting Old(er) in Tech, by Don Denoncourt
-via Hacker News</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GitHub Audio</title>
      <link>https://smutek.net/github-audio/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2016 17:15:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://smutek.net/github-audio/</guid>
      <description> Listen to music generated by events happening across GitHub
 :) Awesome!
github.audio
 via hacker news  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On DRY and the cost of wrongful abstractions</title>
      <link>https://smutek.net/on-dry-and-the-costs-of-wrongful-abstractions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2016 00:22:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://smutek.net/on-dry-and-the-costs-of-wrongful-abstractions/</guid>
      <description>How DRY for the sake of DRY can sometimes lead you down a rabbit hole of madness.
Via hacker news</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A little function for oEmbed &#43; ACF</title>
      <link>https://smutek.net/a-little-function-for-oembed-acf/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Sep 2016 02:18:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://smutek.net/a-little-function-for-oembed-acf/</guid>
      <description>We&amp;rsquo;ve been doing a lot of videos on our sites lately. Well, we&amp;rsquo;ve always done a lot of videos on our sites. The model is usually an on-page embed, either directly in page or via a modal, and we set the back-end up to use the oEmbed field in Advanced Custom Fields Pro. It gives a great back-end experience - and why use WordPress if it&amp;rsquo;s not going to be user configurable, right?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
